A Guide to the Edwin Houston Harman Papers, 1856-1984 (bulk, 1856-1864)
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Edwin Houston Harman Papers, 1856-1984 (Bulk, 1856-1864)
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1990-019
0.5 cu. ft. 1 box
The Edwin Houston Harman Papers consists of letters written in various camps in southwest Virginia to and from Harman and his wife, Jennie. The letters date from 1856 to 1864. There is also a folder of genealogy materials relating to the Harman family.
Harman, Edwin Houston; Harman, Nancy Virginia "Jennie" King, 1838-1910
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The majority of the collection was purchased in May 1990. Additional materials were donated in July 1990.
Biographical Note
Edwin Houston Harman was born February 13, 1835 in Tazewell County. He attended Emory and Henry College. He married Nancy Virginia "Jennie" King of Pulaski County, Virginia on April 2, 1861. He was a Lieutenant colonel in Company H, 45th Virginia Infantry, in the Civil War. He had two children, Charles William Harman (1862-1944) and King Edwin Harman (1863-1939). He was wounded in battle at Cloyd's Mountain, and died two days later on May 11, 1864.
Scope and Content
The Edwin Houston Harman Papers consists of letters written in various camps in southwest Virginia to and from Harman and his wife, Jennie. The letters date from 1856 to 1864. Most of the letters are written to Jennie from Edwin Harman. The letters before 1861 are written before their marriage and are addressed to "Cousin Jennie". The majority of the letters come during the Civil War, and Edwin describes his experiences in the war and the different camps he is staying in. The letters from during the war do include letters from Jennie to Edwin, but the majority of the letters are written to her. After his death in 1864, there are some condolence letters written to Jennie. Included throughout the collection are letters written to Jennie from various family members and close friends.
Also included in the collection are transcripts of some letters that came with the purchase of the material. There is also genealogical material about the Hartman family including biographies, newspaper clippings, letters, and photo slides.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by material type. Within each material type, the collection is arranged chronologically.
Index Terms
Persons:
Harman, Nancy Virginia "Jennie" King, 1838-1910
Family names:
Harman family
Subjects:
Civil War; Cloyds Mountain, Battle of, Va., 1864; Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Pulaski County (Va.); United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865
Contents List
- Letters, 1856-1864, n.d.
  - 1856-1858 (Box-folder 1-1)
  - 1859-1860 (Box-folder 1-2)
  - January to July 1861 (Box-folder 1-3)
  - August to September 1861 (Box-folder 1-4)
  - October to December 1861 (Box-folder 1-5)
  - January to July 1862 (Box-folder 1-6)
  - August to December 1862 (Box-folder 1-7)
  - January to June 1863 (Box-folder 1-8)
  - July to November 1863 (Box-folder 1-9)
  - January to May 1864 (Box-folder 1-10)
  - Undated letters (Box-folder 1-11)
- Transcripts of Letters, 1857-1862
  - August 1857-July 1861 (Box-folder 1-12)
  - August 1861 to December 1861 (Box-folder 1-13)
  - January 1862-September 1862 (Box-folder 1-14)
- Genealogical Material of the Harman Family, 1856-1984 (Box-folder 1-15)